This is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se-radio.net.
SE radio is brought to you by the ITE computer society.
and by it e software magazine online at computer.org/software.
[music]
Hello and welcome to software engineering radio.
My name is Shiran Pam. I'm your host.
Today we have Benjamin Briel, CEO and founder of Cyclloid,
a DevOps platform focused on simplifying and accelerating cloud adoption.
Prior to founding Cyclloid, Ben led sales efforts at Enovans as their first employee before the company was. acquired by Red Hat.
There he held the role of EMA cloud business dev focusing on emerging products like OpenStack. and Open Shift.
Benjamin, welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
Yeah, nice to meet you.
Thank you for the invitation. Always a pleasure to discuss.
Yes, Benjamin, I'm excited to talk to you about internal dev platforms and internal dev portals. Tell us more. What is that?
I mean, let's start with the problems.
The problem are quite simple, right?
DevOps is struggling to scale, right?
We are living definitely in a multi cloud environment.
So, managing on premises, public cloud, private cloud is always a challenge, right?
And there is also a lot of cloud wasted.
right an average of 35 to 45% according to major analysts right.
so based on these problems the goal is to build a portal.
and a platform between the devops on one side and the developer on the other side.
so the goal is to give access to tools cloud automation to end users.
that are not devops and cloud experts right.
and how do you see this problem.
well first of diving more into the problem itself at different stages of a company's life cycle. or the size.
how do you see this problem manifest itself in what ways?
I mean what we see in term of IT transformation people are starting to build some platform engineering.
team right coming from the devops to platform engineering.
we see that githops approach is necessary.
but not enough right generally on IT transformation they are moving from traditional way to managing infrastructures with.
on premises vualization.
and then they start to move to a more devops like GitHubs approach.
but we see that there is some problem of scalability when it comes to devops.
and there is also some problematic of how do you make sure.
that your devops automation is scale right is adopted by end user.
that are not devops and cloud expert.
so in term of I would say adoption there is this need of at which,
[snorts]
stage you are it could be IT transformation.
then it's important to set the stage right to have the right automation.
but it could be also you have developed your own portal.
and you are thinking okay I need to focus on the automation.
and listening my developers to how do I bring them some value.
and less focusing on the portal itself.
rather than the automation and the tool that you are embedded natively inside it right.
you mentioned scalability right like when do you start seeing it let's say a startup with like you. know three they're not going to see this.
They're going to be on a very GitHub focused flow.
But as a scale, where how do you start seeing this pain points?
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean when you start to hire more.
and more developers that you start that you're losing some efficiency.
when it comes to scaffolding some git repository.
that you start to have more and more developer tools that you need to use.
and that you see that with your couple of I would say one two three DevOps guy.
that start to struggle to address the need of developers.
then it start to make sense of course when you're I would say a small startup.
I mean you want to figure out how you provide some value with your platform, right?
With your software and you can handle it with couple of DevOps, right?
But then more your scale doesn't matter.
if you are a scaler or an enterprise there is this needs to on both side.
how do you create some governance within this DevOps team.
We have seen within the pre my previous company.
that starting you know at 15 devops we had different way to do devops.
So the kind of how do you define what is DevOps what is automation is key.
and then comes the topic about IDP portal.
and platform and more you have some developers in front of it.
more you're thinking about okay how can I give them access to tools cloud.
and automation without having being behind all the ticket right.
and what we saw also with our experience is that there is this monitoring ticket right.
if the automation that you created did start to bring more tickets than it's solving.
then then comes maybe the question about how can I give it access to it right.
because yeah let's be honest when you're 20 to 50 you can manage it right couple of dev.
I mean 10 20 developers couple of devops one two three it's manageable right you can handle it.
but then when you start to really scale and or you want to address at the enterprise layer.
then you need to figure out how you give access to tools cloud and automation right.
it's interesting you mentioned the automation that you create to fix bugs creating more bugs right.
so there's two examples I'd love to kind of get from you.
one is what is a good example of an automation.
that is used by teams in an ad hoc way to fix bugs.
and what are some common resultant bugs that come up because of this?
yeah we were kind of a huge adopter of terraform infrastructure as code.
and we see that we created some blueprint.
and then there Comes the question about how do we make the evolution of terapform.
and to maintain the day-to-day operation of terapform right.
yeah we will go later you know as a devops we'll figure out right.
and then we are waiting for the breaking change so you spend a lot of time on it.
and then you can't upgrade all the project in the same thing so one example is just terraform.
or what we have lived also with customers is.
where do you set the border between what does terraform What does Enzible, what does your Kubernetes platform.
and where do you want to invest more to make sure.
that at the end you don't create legacy on automation right.
and we have lived this that we started with Terraform.
but we wanted to also implement the configuration management.
and finally we see that it's exactly the same topic with CI/CD we started with genkins.
and then we bring Argo CD.
but we in the same time implemented some GitHub actions.
because it was kind of and let's even not put the AI topic on the top of all.
of this right.
so at some point more there is some time.
which is passing more there is this needs of taking care about the automation.
and how do you maintain all these stack templating right.
and how do you make sure that you have the inant behind.
that help you to don't maintain the same stack over and over and over.
just because there the new people that are deploying the stack.
that you have created doesn't matter if it goes through portal.
or if it goes through your GitHub's approach right.
here the repo and just use it right.
there is this problematic about I don't want to manage 20,000 times the same repository right.
or the same kind of repositories.
and typically with any development team at least as they grow they don't start to think of their.
platforms as their first go to choice.
they're cobbling things together they just put things together see what works see what doesn't work they they. all these scripts, right?
And one of the metrics, I guess,
that become evident for a team to pause back and say,
"Hey, what we're doing out of our way isn't working."
We need to consider some kind of portalization, I guess.
What would you recommend that is? What would you say that is?
Yeah, it's a good question.
Depends about who you are.
If you are the DevOps team or if you are the dev team, I would say, so I would bring the answer to both of them, right?
Let's go even earlier.
I mean, as a startup or or as any is growing,
they may not even know which side of the divide they're on, right?
I mean first of all there is topic about scorec card.
and how do you evaluate right if you start to feel.
that okay we don't really monitor what we are doing.
we start to see that we are losing sometimes.
when it's onboarding new developers or you know what is the stacks that we are using.
or what is the automation behind and all this kind of typical question.
where the mouse mouse approach doesn't work anymore.
because we know that at human being.
when you pass 50 to 100 people you can't know everybody right.
so there is this kind of structuration between 50 to 150.
where at human size you can't know anymore all the people.
so you can't say yeah just use this and that and it will work right.
so I think there is this when I speak about teams there is this kind of number of.
people first of all.
and also the number of project that you have right.
if it's a one big monolithic or one project then it's kind of easy.
if it's to micros service approach right.
but when you start to see the problem of micros service.
that you don't know who is doing what who is managing what.
and who is owner of which micros service.
and all this stuff then it's this is the right moment.
so I would say those three metrics which is the number of people that you have.
the number of lack of that you're feeling that there is a need of score cap.
and to start to track what happened right.
and the fact that you're starting to ask yourself about.
who is doing what which automation which repository and all this stuff.
then I think it's the right moment to consider what is your strategy right. when it comes to IDP.
yeah and we talked about people we talked about projects.
and there's clearly processes that could be in place both good bad ugly.
and how do you see like existing process kind of fitting in there.
and how do you see the process being both a signal and a call for help?
I mean we do speak a lot of about devops.
and developers first but we don't enough speaking about solution architect.
and that are working to design the processes.
to make sure that it is as smooth as possible especially for organization that have center of excellencies.
that are trying to think about okay which kind of processes should I implement.
because it's not I have to I want to.
but because I have to right if you are a regulated company.
if you are a public institution company.
there is multiple company that are been forced to act in a certain way. Right?
So this is pretty important to make sure.
that the solution architect even the security are embedded in the reflection about which processes.
that I want to take care about all the parties that are integrated.
especially when it's come also to multicloud.
So for example major organization we know.
that everybody have what to say the network the security the architecture team the software team.
and the devops team right.
and there is this need to make sure.
that you have some people doesn't matter.
if you go through githubs approach or if you go through a portal.
that are working to make them glue between all those peoples right.
even if we know that there is a lot of problematics around the politics around budget.
that people don't want to lose their field.
but you can't just you know okay we don't care about it.
this is one of the main problem about adoption of the IDP world.
that are coming from more the dev side they were thinking okay we'll build an IDP.
and then it will be adopted by everyone.
no you won't force the security you won't force the devops you won't force the infrastructures.
that taking care about making running right.
and this is one of the major issue right we come from dev world.
and say let's go it will work right.
and they have to work together right I mean at least is not it is my belly right.
actually I mean I was going to jump into some of the architectural components.
but I'm really curious about the adoption challenges right.
the process the the politics the people right.
so you have this entity that is growing to a size.
where it's realizing that look they're doing a bunch of things and it's kind of not working.
because their velocity metrics are going down their toil is going up.
and they need something is needed right.
so at this point in they either reach out to somebody like yourself.
or you find them through some channel. What happens then?
I think this problem of adoption is not always a question of techniques, right?
It could be also a question of this is my project.
I want to make it work at any cost. Right?
I like to play with new opensource approach. Right?
And we have the same problem internally.
We love to develop everything by our own because we are a tech company, right?
and doesn't matter if you are US.
or European companies when you ask a developer we have this problem what do we do.
they will always say let's develop it right.
it's a fun project right.
and then there is this kind of effect.
that you have with your project because you spend so many effort you know this theory.
that when you have put so many effort to do this.
you don't want to let it down because yeah you're almost there right.
which is kind of one tricky things.
that I see which can be complicated to end which is kind of psychological things right.
and other things when it comes to adoption is that sometimes there is this border of convictions.
let's say I will give you some few example we are githubs based organization.
so everything will go through githubs every developers will go through githubs.
because we will train them to become devops right.
when you have these such convictions right it's complicated to go on.
when you don't want to see something you will find always excuses to don't want to see something.
One example, the other example you can have is that okay, we'll build a center of excellence.
I spent two years to have this center of excellence.
and my 20 people br to make this center of excellence.
and we will build for them the automation.
and it will be adopted right it is the first steps.
but as a human being if you want.
that something is adopted by someone you can't say only okay use what I've done.
you need to help him adopt and use and contribute right to improve what you have done.
and this is a second step which could be really complicated.
because it is how do I build the second stage right.
for example I give you a factual example I build a stack.
or I build a service catalog where I have my landing zone.
and I have the automation on the top of it right.
you have your repository it's scaffolding everything on your g right so use it right.
okay you can use it but let's say as a developer I want to change it for my. business unit.
because how do I make this change about everything that you have gave me without breaking everything.
Right.
So this is some question that is always difficult to handle.
when you have spent so much time to build your service catalog.
and then for example another example is you build some forms right doesn't matter.
if you do it yourself or if you do it through a portal.
you build some forms and then you ends up with 10,000 forms how do you manage the day-to-day. operation right.
how do you make sure that they don't redevelop something that have been already developed right.
because we see on big organization we have this capability to redo.
and redo and redo all the time the same things modulo the five 10% you know custom.
so one of the big challenge I would say.
when it comes to adoption is to make sure that we don't only think for ourself. but we also think for others.
and how do you make sure that they can contribute to what you have done.
and not only here I expose you what you done doesn't matter your strategy API first back end. first.
you don't need a front end or you in the front end.
or you do it yourself, right?
Is how do you make sure that it's not your project,
it's a project that you will be part of, right?
Which is the success of open source, right?
Like it's not your project, it's something that you can contribute and then you scale, right? It's my belief, right?
It's interesting you mentioned center of excellence.
because in a lot of the companies a center of excellence ends up becoming this single point.
from which ideas kind of emerge or ideas are meant to emerge, right? And typically you might have a case.
where they're addressing a certain problem but as the problem space moves within the company.
the 80% 90% case that they are charged with solving might no longer be the problem statement. Right?
And the case you mentioned where you have thousand forms coming up or thousand different implementations coming up.
It's almost like a reaction to what was before but what is not being addressed today.
Right?
So I guess that's where it sounds like IDPs come in with a set of recommendations on how.
these processes can be standardized and measured.
So now that a entity you know small big medium large has decided that they need something.
right and they reach out to somebody who's experienced in building IDPs.
so what next like what does a implementation look like for them.
they don't they want it they don't know what it is what do they do?
I mean we still have some customers.
which are working I would say through a traditional VMware approach or whatever virtualization with all the automation.
which is not really based on open source that saying okay let's do some IDP or whatever.
and I always explain them there is no tools.
that exist that will do the trick for you if you don't have people behind right doesn't work.
so you need to invest on DevOps platform team whatever you call it.
that has both the capability to leverage your automation create your automation but also evangelize right.
because what you don't want on this role is someone which is focusing only on the tech aspect.
but Don't work with your end users to have a recurring loop of we are working as a. team.
I'm here to serve you and I'm here to make you something that at some point makes sense. Right.
On that quickly, what does that anti pattern look like in real life in one of your,
[snorts]
implementations? Yeah. Yeah.
I mean, the auntie is hiring some huge tech expert.
that don't want to speak to anyone out of this code, right?
and then it ends up doing some really nice tech things.
but can maybe miss the point about what is your need right explain me right.
and what I've seen through my career is.
that the best tech guy are not the best generally not the best speaker guy right.
the guy that you want to discuss with.
that will come to see to speak to you to help me understand what you need.
and how you use it.
and I will explain you how you should use it and how you can contribute.
So it's always you need to have people.
that does the automation and you have to have people that explain it and work with the team, right?
And it's always complicated to find the everybody want the sheep that does everything, right?
But there is no 50 sheep, right?
You can have maybe one or two, right, that are top guys.
but at some point evangelization is not something.
that you should avoid or you think because you're developing something which is completely beauty.
Doesn't matter if you buy it or if you build it that it will be adopted by yourself, right?
It has to invest on people and product.
It's not only a product topic, right?
Right.
but if you look at the architecture of a typical IDP,
when an enterprise decides to take one, what would you recommend is the ideal architecture?
or are there stages of evolution that you would recommend? Like where does that fall in?
If you're designing one from scratch today, how would you go about this?
I mean, you should be completely agnostic from your cloud infrastructures.
So doesn't matter if it's onrem, public cloud, kubernetes or whatever.
But what you're designing should be completely agnostic for it, right?
You should be thinking it's only this or that, right?
Because what could be true today can be wrong tomorrow, right?
Let's say you're a startup, you're only on a cloud provider and then you acquire another company,
he's on another cloud provider, then okay.
or you are a major organizations.
You say, "Yeah, today we only do this cloud plus the onrem.
and then you have a new bus and say, you know, now it's not this one, right?
It's another cloud provider, right?"
So, first agnosticity of the cloud.
Second, open source automation, right?
You don't want to have your automation which is linked to a vendor or a constructor of hardware.
because by definition if they investing on a software which is linked to your you know low layer.
you can make sure that they won't work to be as agnostic as possible.
they will invest on definitely their architecture.
and then there is this topic of portal.
and platform where at some point it should be also completely agnostic from the automation.
and And there is this strategy of build it versus buy it.
You should ask yourself the important question.
Okay, if I build it when it's open source, is it really open source? Is it sovereign?
Does it respect the opensource strategy?
Meaning multiple contributor from enterprise market behind, right?
Because individual contributor is great, right?
But it doesn't what scale an enterprise opensource project, right?
You need to have strong partners and vendors that are supporting this.
or if you buy it you should find something that is enough flexible to not lock you.
because like a full product which is our concern right is not something.
that you want to be capable to customize what you have bought right.
so this is the kind of typical architecture right that you can embed.
and then there is this open question about where do you set the border between portal and platform.
If you are coming from the cloud management world to the IDP world,
could you find something that make the glue?
because otherwise you will have two different software that will have to communicate.
and then you can create some more automation that is complex to handle and all this stuff.
So there is no tools that does everything right or no software that does everything.
That's a really good segue.
I mean where do you draw the line between portal versus platform.
and how would I as a customer know the difference?
What I would say is that portal is the dev world and platform is the devops world right.
but as an end user you don't want to take care about all the automation behind.
and you want to make sure that just like.
when you are using something it's respect best practices at organization layer.
and what I see is that this is our play I'm not here to talk. too much about cyloid.
but I never understood how you can separate the both of them right.
because a portal we already have it.
It's called Firefox, right? You can have all your.
It's the UI and API again, right?
Yeah. Yeah. Things needs to communicate each other.
Self-service portal can't be separated to the orchestration layer.
Otherwise, again, you create some friction between the portal and the platform which is normal. It's a market overview.
Let's be honest.
US way of designing software are quite of simple.
They are saying we are coming from the de world.
We'll build the developer tools interface and then we will force devops.
What we have seen so far is that you don't force DevOps.
don't force infrastructures and on the infrastructure say you had the cloud management platform world.
that is kind of dead.
with all the devops and multicloud world that trade right.
so I think you should figure out how you can build them bridge between this IDP and CMP. and doesn't matter if you buy it.
or build it finding something that don't create more work that you want to solve right.
and let's not even speak about AI on the top of it right.
I don't think you're going to have any talk.
or chat a podcast without AI at some point in time.
Bonus points if you do.
But going back to the divide between portal. and platform and UI and API and.
so how would you describe the technical components of this architecture that can unify that?
You mentioned principles like being cloud agnostic, being open source friendly, being enabling customizability.
but what about a good IDP architecture can actually enable.
that like what would be the components like key components.
So in term of software first there is this service catalog right building blocks.
that you need to build right behind it.
you need to have an engine that is capable to version everything.
that you have done the versioning aspect.
otherwise you will have to maintain multiple stacks which are kind of the same.
then you need to have the platform orchestration which is how do you orchestrate.
and how to make sure that you have a currency between all the tools that you're.
Then you have I would believe an asset inventory approach.
which is how do you make sure that you give a 360 visibility about your environment.
doesn't matter if it's onrem public cloud and all this stuff.
then there is this topic which I believe.
that we need to be tackled is the phopups and greenups module.
at some point you want to evangelize your developer.
and anyone which are not devops and cloud expert even the devops to your cloud cost impact.
and your cabin impact. Right?
Because in the next couple of years you will have some trade-off about you can't deploy here.
because you didn't pay enough right.
so you had to decide where you want you are capable to deploy especially with the raise of.
AI that are really high consuming in term of resources.
and then there is this scaffolding approach right.
where you need to make sure that the interaction between what you are doing.
and everything that you have on your git repository respect some structure.
otherwise anyone that or deploying a new project will face some difficulties.
when it comes to find a new project or find a project that is already exist.
all this aspect about scaffolding and to finish I'm a strong believer about AI as an assistant not. as a do it for you right.
and as an assistant to make sure.
that when others are using what you are doing you have a capable to have a feedback loop.
that is capable to make sure that it's respecting best practices it's respecting your API of course the.
documentation that should be linked to it documentation logs.
and to finish to be capable able for anyone to contribute to what you have done is to.
give them the aspect of plug-in system, right?
Where you should be capable to give them the capability to create some plugins in a simple way. that is manageable, right?
Because as a platform team, you will never be able to address 100% of the use case, right? It will never exist, right?
You can try as hard as you want.
It's not possible because you will have always someone.
or a business unit that will tell you yeah it's lovely what you have done.
but I want this and that and that right.
so you need to build an engine.
that is capable to handle this capability to integrate some custom needs. that you would never be capable to enter right.
and to finish the last piece on the top of it is the capability to measure what you. have done and to collaborate on it.
to be capable able to have some clear feedback loop within what you are doing.
You know I'm not speaking only about a link to your you know Slack.
or whatever you are using in term of instant messenger.
I mean a system that is capable to work as a road map system within your product to.
make sure that you give the capability.
to also help you improve what you have done right.
and to communicate on it to interact to save some time for both the dev.
and the deops when you you know you want to help them working together.
The analogy I can think of is it is a lot easier to launch rockets from space than.
it is from Earth, right?
So you want to get your rockets to space as quickly and fast and cheaply as possible, right?
And a lot of this integration is kind of that because once they have an IDP in place,
they get all the benefits, but how do you get them there?
How do you get these customers kind of onboarding onto your IDP.
or even getting like forming things in a very left shifted way so they can start using it?
So again if you think about customers you know building their own service you know using gRPC.
or rest or whatnot in custom frameworks.
how do you make integrations easy for them.
so no matter where they are you can meet them there like what can you do?
use simple things that are natively automated you can't ask them to understand all your ecosystem it has.
to be simple it has to be one good use cases.
being capable to also integrate in the vibe coding approach.
where you should be able to test and try and fail fast.
before you want to invest heavily on a plug-in or you know.
you need to be capable to diagnostic from any languages.
because if you force the language you can make sure.
that the guys say oh no I want to use this and not that.
because we have the expertise and blah blah blah.
So this plus the fact that you need to have people.
that evangelize that explain that go to see the team that go to see the members.
that okay we have done that you can do this you can't request everything from the platform.
that you are building.
you need to have people that are willing.
and want to spend some times with people that are not devops and cloud expert.
so it's a multiffactor approach to help sure.
that your platform that you are building is.
also serving the interest of someone which are clearly not devops and cloud exper.
and it is really complex because let's be honest like developers like to develop on day languages.
and it's also a question of habit a question of knowledge.
and question of convictions you know I'm a pro react.
or I'm a pro view or I'm a pro go and or I'm pro++.
you can't compete against that you need to adapt to okay.
if you want to do that this is the schema that you have to respect.
I will help you make sure that you can do this.
and that and keep your you know things.
and of course if you develop something.
that at the end help the end user adopt faster.
and are capable to create some plug-in in more easil way better.
it is I'm a strong believer that the best UI experience is the UI.
where where you don't have to explain everything to the end customers to the end user.
and that it's obvious that okay you know I can do this in a simple way.
which is the beauty of UI and UX.
and which is the complex things because developing something.
which is simple and flexible this is the most complicated things.
and this is where we see I would say the lack of capability of AI.
that are not designed and thought to make something simple they're working on patterns.
and we see that the way of how it is created.
so we can't achieve to have this beauty of a strong UIX UI approach.
with people that thought about okay the simple is the better the smoother right.
and I mean when people tell me you know AI will replace UI I say we are not. living in the same world right.
I mean if you ask me the best UI is CLI.
[laughter]
so there is still lot of work to do right.
yeah so you mentioned schema registry right schema registry or schemas and again meeting where they are.
So with your service catalog approach and having a schema issue like how does a customer kind of. get to a point.
where they are ready to be part of the service catalog.
like what do they have to overcome like what gravitational forces do they have to overcome to get.
to space as an end user or as a debubs.
bit of both like if you if you think about your customer.
right they have to onboard onto your IDP.
and again starting from where they are they are nowhere near.
and they need to build up something to get to be ready.
to have a service catalog that they can start off from.
there is fewer princip project that if they have some infrastructure which obviously they have.
they can reverse some terraforms on the fly like we have for example an open source project.
which is called Terraonita.
you connect it to your cloud and it generates automation for you on your flight.
it won't do like 100% of the job because you will have some requirement as an organization.
but it will help you maybe to have the first layer of automation.
so you need to have at least some automation Doesn't matter.
if it's infrastructure as code configuration management and or you know CI/CD pipelines.
you need to have a GitHub first approach.
If you don't have GitHubs most probably your IDP topic will never comes.
because it is linked GitHubs first approach.
then I generally build an IDP on the top of it.
I mean to me with a service catalog you still starting off with a service.
and for a service you'll need some kind of API interface. that you want to define and share.
of course or spec you want to share.
So if a team has that let's say gRPC.
or an open API spec or a respect right is that sufficient.
or is it still a long way to go before that becomes part of your service catalog?
No it could be really simple like you know the landing zone everybody is speaking about landing zone.
it's a simple things.
but behind this landing zone you could have multiple aspect about the security the governance the cloud provider. and all this stuff.
So of course you want to have at the end some stacks with security network infrastructures application layer.
that is as flexible as possible right.
but a simple use case which is the base of everything.
that we are deploying a landing zone or you know the set of tools that we have right.
for example I don't know as a developer I need to get access to my 10 tools as.
a developer to develop right.
or VDI topic right or scaffolding some new project.
It's not something complicated but takes some time.
You can easily build some stacks around this without you know overink about which kind of service catalog.
It's things that you are using all the time.
So I would say the most simple one is landing zone and tools that the developer are using.
Yeah.
And one thing you mentioned that's interesting was security.
How do you see security and or lack of play a role in both the adoption. and friction against IDP?
What we see in term of security is.
that security is also taking the path of security as cut like we saw premium software whatever.
everything has cutgo policy and stuff like this.
So there is this huge need of a GitHub first approach.
Of course, security like at the time were more focusing on compliances.
and you know bend and software plus hardware right.
but we see that with the raise of uh cloud there is more and more security as code.
and as soon as you add this approach as code you can embed it everywhere inside your pipeline.
inside your stack inside your policy management everywhere right.
but more we are diving in the I would say the cave of infrastructures more the ascode is. less obvious let's be honest.
but what we see and what we didn't see a couple of years ago is.
that this initiative can even come from the security team.
that came you know or the network team for example.
that want to give access to everything.
that they have done in a simple way because they know that they will never understand a clue.
about everything that we are designing.
because it's a world like the security aspect,
the network aspect if you you can't scratch it.
or you understand what happened or you're in the matrix.
So we see some teams that are coming on this path.
that go as code and go for a self-service approach.
to give access to everything that they have done respecting best practices which is GitHub's first design approach. Right?
This sounds like there is still a bit of leg work.
that teams have to do to adopt a security as code culture, right?
But for and I'm going to go on a limb here for a big proportion of the population.
that is not adopting this culture.
how do you get them over that hurdle so they can be IDP ready?
I mean our conviction is that you should respect the borders and the competencies of each business unit.
and your platform should be capable to include the complexity of this big organization.
and this is one of the key adoption right.
for example on our side we have some forms those forms are presented for the end user with.
10 different teams behind.
the one that are handling the CI/CD the one.
that the network the one that are doing the security aspect and all this stuff.
and again you can't request everything from everyone becoming the expert of everyone.
It's not possible when you have 5,000 or or 10,000 IT team, right?
You can't expect everybody expert from everything. It doesn't scale.
It's not the case and it's obviously not possible.
So your software should be capable to handle this capability of you present your work.
but you are working in an ecosystem. You are not alone.
That is why again GitHubs by design.
and your IDP should be capable to interact with your automation below.
and that is why we are a strong believer about the open source automation. which we linked to it.
So is there a risk that that you could end up becoming a you know a center of.
excellence and kind of becoming that bottleneck in day-to-day process.
like how do you manage that risk?
I mean as a software yes definitely it's a huge challenge to do it yourself right.
I mean people started with couple of guys let's develop an IDV.
right how do you want obviously to compete with you know software vendor.
that have you know 40 100 developers for time that are pushing so hard on it right.
let's be tangible on it a bit it is really complicated and the ecosystem world is is huge.
but what is interesting again is that on this AI high topic is the capability to test. and try and fail fast.
to don't look for the the performance the beauty of the code the you know day-to-day operation.
and don't create depth you will.
but through AI you can test and try.
and see if it's adopted and everyone can you know with few vibe coding develop something.
that he thought and he present.
and then let's monitor it to see if it's used or not.
and then if it's used let's invest some developers to do it right.
and I think between this mix of decreasing time to test I would say time to use.
and see if it makes sense the time to market.
then you invest some developers to make something respecting the best practices doesn't matter if it's on prem.
I mean if it's do it yourself or through a software vendor right.
I think we touch upon the cultural challenges of adoption the people side of it the organizational side.
of it what about technical.
like again people want to adopt they're really excited about this what's been the most technically challenging adoption.
that you had uh go through with the most excited and the most enthusiastic customer.
I mean the biggest issue that we have with lot of customers is the internal battle between on. premises and cloud.
which are generally not the for enterprise market not the same one right which is normal right.
let's say you have done 20 years of traditional virtualization you are used to you know do some. not tips.
but to go through a new UI that make the magics for your right.
and it's working and then we're kind of used to a little bit of insatisfaction.
Right?
Then you're saying okay now you do some CI/CD infrastructure as code configuration management security as code.
and you will help anyone be capable to adopt and contribute to what you have done.
Of course they will say no and they will find thousand of excuses why cloud is not good.
and why or onrem is not good.
So they're fighting against each other, right?
Which is true, but that's like a cultural organizational issue though, not a technical problem, right?
Yeah.
And the biggest challenge is how do you make sure.
that you have and this is why drift control exist.
and how do you make sure that you cover as much as possible the automation for your infrastructures.
doesn't matter if it's on prem and public cloud, right?
on Kubernetes it's really complex because you still had some mainframe you still have some tools.
that you want to deprovision but you can't provision it.
let's keep an example genkins right everybody want to go out from genkins for good. or bad reason right.
but yeah they want to move and you say.
okay how many project do you have 7,000 it will take a little bit some time to move.
from you know.
so how do you provide the unify experience to make sure.
that as an enterprise you don't take some decision.
that the end will be achieved in the next 5 to 10 years, right?
You need to be capable to provide a unified experience, right?
And this is a technical challenge because if we take just one pass which is Kubernetes, right?
As a market, we say forget the traditional app,
you know, let's only care about native cloud application, it's the future, you will migrate everything, right? It didn't.
Obviously in the market Kubernetes as you know you know five 10 years ago it was huge like.
everybody were kubernetes right.
and then when you speak to the customers at enterprise layer say what is the percentage of kubernetes.
application that you have ready couple of%. Wow.
So this is technical challenge that how do you build the gap between traditional environment.
that are not devops and githubs ready right the native one right.
of course the new one will be native right and more devops and githops oriented.
but how do you make sure that mainframe.
and all the traditional work I mean cobalt is already is still existing right in multi-bank right.
it's not in the plan to change it.
because if you touch it you're scared that you know whatever.
So the biggest technical challenge that I see is.
that you provide a unified experience doesn't matter.
if you are using traditional tools and application right and infrastructures.
and the day to native bonding the cloud application infrastructure and this is the biggest things.
because there is huge customers that face this problematic about how do I integrate my legacy within my.
IDP topic right. you almost sounds like if the biggest challenge.
that you have is technical that's a really good problem to have.
because typically it's a combination of technical cost organization you know TCO.
and you never really find one axis that takes over all three.
I mean it's a really interesting project for everyone for the management.
you know bringing the IT team not only as a cost.
but also as a providing some solution to help you know the developers.
it's also interesting in term cost approach right.
because at some point with the sovereign topic you need to mitigate your risk with the current US. ecosystem right now.
and you don't want to be linked to one provider doesn't matter.
who you are right Asian As European or US organization right.
so I mean what we see on this topic about the IDP.
which is cycl is that there is a huge people want to go make something.
that makes sense right.
both dev and devops.
and it's kind of finally find a a middle ground where people can speak right.
because automation right okay well learn it.
or you know use it right I don't want to learn I am not.
and I don't have time to learn and I don't understand how to use it right.
you don't want it to become a N plus one problem.
yeah yeah definitely changing gears I have a billion dollar question for you.
well actually a trillion dollar question AI. I think that's got to at all right.
where do you see AI impact IDP.
or vice versa and what does it mean for you as a company.
so we've seen a trend that is say you know IDP is dead welcome AI agent software.
right do I buy this or not clearly not.
I think organization and people are looking for more people right more interaction right.
and do you really want to discuss with the bot whatever the intelligence that they have behind right.
I don't buy is they're also looking to cut cost though.
Yeah.
But do you really want as a an IDP having some features.
that help the developer the devops to save some time when it comes to AI?
Yes, I buy this, right?
Yes, I buy the capability to develop some plug-in as fast as possible.
Yes, I buy the AI that are drilling all the you know test.
and make sure that it's respecting the documentation your API.
and you know saving some time for both dev and devops. Yeah, but at some point do I buy.
that AI will replace a really nice way UIX UI interface? No, I don't.
I don't because to buy this meaning.
that people will have to understand all the process to design build migrate and run.
doesn't matter if it's onrem traditional application tools and cloud.
no you develop an interface to simplify the way to be capable to interact with this.
and through an LLM whatever you know.
you don't want having someone and you will never have someone okay I want to do this. and that and that and that and that.
and then taking in consideration that at every equation.
that you have you have a 8 to 10 second wait right.
but some would say that that's a feature I mean I may.
or not agree with that but like some say.
that's what the defining quality of AI today is that simplified chat interface.
we'll see what is the future my bet is the next 12 to 18 months you will have.
an AI crash right.
which will lead to all the VC fund enterprise software that have been overrated on their valuation.
Most probably we will have 80% of VC that will bankrupt right.
and now what we see is that as a global economy VCs.
and private equity are looking for profitable company right.
so at some point paid by our customers right.
and there is this huge problem about the AOI and the level of investment.
that have been made by the AI market in front of the revenue that they generated right.
and based on few papers that you can easily find on internet.
if you take off all the AI investment that have been made in the US.
the US is in recession, right?
Economically wise, right?
So I mean there is this huge question about how does an organization is realable over the time, right?
And we see that on the last five years,
three years since the covid like the startup ecosystem took a huge eat.
like you know between 50 to 70% yearon-year decrease investment.
out of the AI bubble then you know I don't know what I see is.
that people are explaining me that you know well AIG will take longer.
maybe will not happen the way of how we have built the LLM or not enough good.
We should rethink the way of how we structure it.
We'll see, right? I mean, I think your countryman Yan Lakun has some good points for sure.
And let's not even mention about the carbon impact.
and the multiriteria impact that he has in term of limit of resources, right?
We know that by 2030 the capability for data AI.
that double every 6 months will won't be possible, right?
And there is this problem about data.
do you inject and the level of data.
that are generating with LLM and all the problem of LM right.
and do you really want that on your infrastructures there is a marge of errors right.
and you know my belief is that we should always keep human in the loop.
right that at some point we should have someone.
and understand what happened and that you don't want to create some technical depth right.
which is one of the main challenge alto about AI code generated.
right is how do you make sure that you have someone that understand what has been done.
that can read that can challenge and can make some change right.
and this is a collective I would say challenge that we have when we use AI right.
is the where do we set the border between a junior and or a senior expert developer right.
is how do you use it how do you make sure.
that you don't create some security issues right security.
and AI we can spend an we're discussing this right.
on that note though like I mean with the current state of AI.
and whether it's a bubble or not.
how would you or anybody implementing/ integrating IDBs like how would you hedge that bet.
like what would you do to hedge that bet?
I mean you need to understand what you're doing for me AI is a tool right.
if you want to use the tool know how to use it right.
know how to do it and know what this tool is capable to do right.
you need to know what you are doing right you can't rely on something that you don't understand.
and this is the only advice if you want to build.
and or implementing some AI functions inside your IDP.
is make sure that you control what you are doing right.
and that you keep human in the loop.
because if you wipe your GitHubs based.
because AI made a mistake you will have to face the consequences right.
and we are not speaking about theoretically. Right?
We know that AI is capable to understand that they made a mistake.
Not really know how why but I think keeping always the human inoop is really necessary.
otherwise I mean I'm coming from the infrastructure world.
So I'm more kind of private medical guy rather than you know de first oriented. You should be careful with what you're doing, right?
Especially as we are speaking about infrastructures and you know that already bring a lot of power right.
I mean infrastructure as code is already a lot of power right.
so you can you know delete a world project right like doesn't exist anymore right.
so what I will say is again understand what you are implemented make sure.
that you don't suff on the I.
because again you will be judged on the ROI right.
and you should monitor and make sure that what you are doing is makes sense.
and that you should keep your sovereignty approach.
because otherwise the money that you spend right now you will have to pay it much more later.
because we know that today AI business model are not profitable.
and one way or the others we always know that it is the customers that pay.
Yep. Yep.
I'm sure this is a topic that we can talk on for hours with pleasure.
As we come to a close uh what about IDPs.
and platform engineering that I mean what are other areas that our customers should be aware of.
and can dig more into in term of IDP and platform engineering?
you should really you know work within your organization to understand your pain point don't focus on the.
market trend.
you know we have to the same as AI right what is the problem.
that you want to solve. let's go back to the essential what is the problem.
that you want to solve and before building a rocket right let's build the first stage.
because we always have a lot of you know architect that build the rocket right.
but let's start with step one right.
and make sure that we learn by doing things which I believe is really important.
because sometimes you know we can buy huge project with a lot of investment.
and then you know comes the problem of a right.
so it's not fancy but is again asking the good question.
which problem do I want to solve and how do I solve it.
before looking for a tools that will doesn't matter the tools help you work on this problem.
I mean this is what I would think about it.
and our listeners on the show how can they learn more about platform engineering how can they learn.
more about IDP and cyclloid?
I mean on our website the documentation is completely open right we have some open source project.
that you can use it for free.
we won't up the licensing model just because you are using an open source project, right?
I mean, you can test and try definitely without any issues. So, I mean, it's a win-win situation, right?
Will you be speaking at any upcoming conference.
or events where folks could hear more from you on these topics?
Today, we are at Gartner conference in London.
will be in two weeks in the Gartner the developer environment also ecosystem.
and in France we'll be also in the DevOps Rex.
where we will have some Rex with one of our big customers.
that have implemented this IDP topic right.
and for our listeners we'll link everything that Ben mentioned in the show notes. any final thoughts for our uh audience?
thank you for listening if you arrive until here right.
if you arrive until here and you listen my word.
you can write me directly and I will send you some goodies for free.
because it's 1 hour 8 minutes.
So I mean this is really good.
Just drop me some message on LinkedIn and you will receive some goodies for free. Right.
Thank you very much Ben. It's been fantastic having you. This is Shiran Pam from Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you for listening.
Thank you for your inviting Richie.
[music]
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an educational program brought to you by E Software Magazine.
For more about the podcast, including other episodes, visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on LinkedIn,
Facebook, Twitter, or through our Slack channel at seradio.slack.com.
[music]
You can also email us at teamse-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio is licensed under Creative Common License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.
[music]